<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <!-- what -->
  The OME Java Server is a port of some of the OME Data Server (OMEDS) Perl code to Java. 
  Specifically, it replaces the object-relational mapping code named "DBObject" with existing object-relational mapping (ORM) tools. 
  The change frees us from the maintenance of self-written code which has been the basis of the project for the last X years.
  As a project code, it becomes necessary to focus ever more carefully on the offered specialty.
  Though DBObject has served us well, there are simply other development teams who specialize in OR mapping and it has become time to look into these existing options.
  
  <!-- why -->
  <para>
    In addition to the reduced developer load, the choice of alternative existing O/R implementations such as  Hibernate or Java Data Objects (JDO), 
    the compiled language and more extensive feature list bring significant performance gains.
  </para>
  
  <section id="intro-info">
    <title>Project Information</title>
    <programlisting>
LICENSE

    OME is distributed with the GNU Lesser General Public License
    (LGPL). You should be aware that any code submitted to the OME
    project will also fall under this license. If you have issues
    relating to licensing, want to sub license parts of the OME source
    code, or wish to discuss the licensing scheme please contact the
    OME core developers (ome-devel@lists.openmicroscopy.org.uk).

COPYRIGHT

    The OME source code, specification, documentation and database schema are,
    in their entirety Copyright (C) 2003 Open Microscopy Environment,
    Massachusetts Institute of Technology, National Institutes of Health,
    University of Dundee. As with the OME license, any questions related to the
    copyright, copyright holders or copyright scheme should be directed to the
    OME core developers (ome-devel@lists.openmicroscopy.org.uk).

DEVELOPER LOCATIONS

    The OME core developers are split between three main locations: OME Boston
    (MIT and Harvard; managed by Peter Sorger and Erik Brauner), OME Dundee
    (University of Dundee; managed by Jason Swedlow) and OME Baltimore (NIH;
    managed by Ilya Goldberg).

RESOURCES

    Most of the OME developer related documentation is either in the
    source tree (/doc and pod in the source files) or located on the
    CVS webserver (http://cvs.openmicroscopy.org.uk/).  There is also
    a documentation website available at
    http://docs.openmicroscopy.org.uk/.

LINKS

	The OME Project:  http://www.openmicroscopy.org/
	OME developers:   http://cvs.openmicroscopy.org.uk/
	Web based CVS:    http://cvs.openmicroscopy.org.uk/cvsweb/
	Documentation:    http://docs.openmicroscopy.org.uk
	Bug Tracker:      http://bugs.openmicroscopy.org.uk

MAILING LISTS

	OME developers:   ome-devel@lists.openmicroscopy.org.uk

      </programlisting>
  </section>


</chapter>

