<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <section id="introduction-what">
    <title>What?</title>
    <para>
      The OME java server is a port of the perl code make use of existing object-relational mapping (ORM) tools. 
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="introduction-why">
    <title>Why?</title>
    <para>
      Speed, ease of development, agility, alternative implementations
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="introduction-how">
    <title>How?</title>
    <para>
      Just what are these implementations? Well,...
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="intro-blurb">
    <title>Other info</title>
    <programlisting>
LICENSE

    OME is distributed with the GNU Lesser General Public License
    (LGPL). You should be aware that any code submitted to the OME
    project will also fall under this license. If you have issues
    relating to licensing, want to sub license parts of the OME source
    code, or wish to discuss the licensing scheme please contact the
    OME core developers (ome-devel@lists.openmicroscopy.org.uk).

COPYRIGHT

    The OME source code, specification, documentation and database schema are,
    in their entirety Copyright (C) 2003 Open Microscopy Environment,
    Massachusetts Institute of Technology, National Institutes of Health,
    University of Dundee. As with the OME license, any questions related to the
    copyright, copyright holders or copyright scheme should be directed to the
    OME core developers (ome-devel@lists.openmicroscopy.org.uk).

DEVELOPER LOCATIONS

    The OME core developers are split between three main locations: OME Boston
    (MIT and Harvard; managed by Peter Sorger and Erik Brauner), OME Dundee
    (University of Dundee; managed by Jason Swedlow) and OME Baltimore (NIH;
    managed by Ilya Goldberg).

RESOURCES

    Most of the OME developer related documentation is either in the
    source tree (/doc and pod in the source files) or located on the
    CVS webserver (http://cvs.openmicroscopy.org.uk/).  There is also
    a documentation website available at
    http://docs.openmicroscopy.org.uk/.

LINKS

	The OME Project:  http://www.openmicroscopy.org/
	OME developers:   http://cvs.openmicroscopy.org.uk/
	Web based CVS:    http://cvs.openmicroscopy.org.uk/cvsweb/
	Documentation:    http://docs.openmicroscopy.org.uk
	Bug Tracker:      http://bugs.openmicroscopy.org.uk

MAILING LISTS

	OME developers:   ome-devel@lists.openmicroscopy.org.uk

      </programlisting>
  </section>


</chapter>

